Hi, it's Craig here, and it's Josh.
Yo, where are we going to be?
Uh, bringing you through our HTML5 introduction course.
It's a very exciting course.
The objective of this course is to teach you the basics of HTML5, what it's about, and how you can
get to actually be a coder of HTML and set up your first website.
So let's have a quick overview of what we're going to cover.
We're going to in this first section, uh, start in our first section is an introduction to HTML,
how it works, how it's put together an editor that you can use, all the basics that you get comfortable.
Very important.
When you sit down to a meal, you want to be comfy, uh, then we'll start looking at formatting images
and, um, how we can change the sizes, how we can add images.
And then equipped with that, you're just about ready to put together your first couple of web pages
into our website.
So our third section is going to look at essentially putting this all together and creating your first
website.
Then we'll be looking at tables, backgrounds and more.
So this is going to be basically how to make your website look nice and neat.
Not have everything just lying around.
Putting a background a little bit like Josh's room.
Sometimes you don't want it all lying around.
I mean, if you could organize your life and your room much like a HTML website, I mean, it could
look really neat.
So that's that section.
And then, well, buttons, links, sizing and so much more.
We'll get a little bit more involved when we look at how you can link pages together, create buttons,
change the sizes of images, etc...
Now just to get straight, this is an introductory course.
You're not going to be at the end of this like, hey, I'm a master.
I am the Jedi of all programming developers for web pages.
The idea is it's to introduce you to the basics.
But at the end of this, we want you to be comfortable with working with HTML.
And once you're comfortable with working with it, there are so many options to go further as we will
explore in this lesson and others afterwards.
So you must have a question and the obvious question that is in your mind is yes, that's exactly it.
What is HTML5?
Why is it five?
Why is it not four?
Three?
Two?
One?
Why has it even got a number?
What's it all about?
That is a really good question.
And of course, if you were an active learner, I'm going to encourage you in this course.
If you're an active learner, you would actually go and Google that.
I dare you.
Come on, I dare you.
Pause now and go Google it.
Right.
So what did you find out?
Well, you discovered, didn't you, that HTML5 is actually essentially made up of three parts.
It's the HTML part, the CSS which stands for cascading.
Did you look it up?
Stylesheets and JS which stands for JavaScript.
Right.
So these are the three parts that make up HTML5.
HTML5 is in fact an environment.
So HTML essentially is what allows your websites to to talk to each other to, to understand what's
actually going on.
And we'll look at that in a moment.
Then next to that there is a CSS, which as I said, is Cascading Style Sheets CSS.
Josh, what's what's that all about?
So CSS is basically like um, well with HTML, like you can make your website look really good just
with HTML and then with CSS.
Basically this is how you put lots of like little effects and styles and animations and all of that
kind of stuff that just makes your website look even more beautiful.
So if HTML is like the skeleton, then CSS is the skin, is the skin that goes over it.
And then of course, if you want it to have motion, to have heart to have the beating heart that's
pumping inside there, that's giving it life, ultimately you need JS, which is JavaScript, and this
is really where you're starting to code things that are going to do, the processing that sits behind
and inside the skeleton and the skin.
So that's HTML5.
HTML5 is made up of HTML, CSS and JavaScript.
But on this course we're not going to be looking at CSS and JavaScript.
We're going to be looking at HTML because that's where it all starts.
That is the foundation.
So very quickly to explain to you how this works.
HTML is essentially code.
It's code that sits on a page much like you see here.
And it really is computer code.
It's code that allows one computer to understand what another one is saying.
And this code is passed around and that code is then sent through to a browser.
And inside the browser it interprets this code, which is what we're going to be learning.
And it displays it in a certain way.
So essentially all that HTML is, is a series of codes.
It's a programming language that a browser can interpret and then know how to display things.
So for example, it will say I want a picture and I want the picture to be over here, I want some text
and I want the text to be over here.
That's all written as code, which is HTML, Hypertext Markup Language.
And then whichever browser you are using, whether it be Chrome or Explorer or Safari or whatever,
will then interpret that code and display it.
So we're going to be learning about HTML and how we can create basic websites.
So first look at that.
That's pretty exhausting.
What do you say Josh.
Yeah it looks very confusing.
And you've probably come across it at different stages.
You know, if you at any stage look at the source code behind a web page, this is what's behind the
web pages.
It looks exhausting, like, wow, what is going on there?
But we're going to see in a moment.
It's actually not that hard.
Once you understand the basics of how HTML works, it's actually quite easy and you are about to become
empowered to become an HTML coder.
So here's an example of a segment of HTML code.
Again, looks like wow, what is going on here?
It really is, is quite simple.
So essentially all HTML code is made up of is a series of tags.
So you'll see there is a tag.
A tag is something that occurs between those little brackets those little diagonal type brackets.
So here we have a tag called head.
But now for every tag or for most of them, for every opening tag, there will be a closing tag.
Closing tag is preceded with a forward slash.
So you can see here we've got a forward slash head and head is the opening tag.
So if you look around you should be able to see some others opening and closing tags here we've got
one that doesn't look as obvious.
And there we can see the closing tag.
But again that is our tag there.
It's opened even though there's some other little components to it.
Don't worry about the moment, but there's the close.
See any others?
Yes, there's an H1 tag, the close, the open and on and on ago.
So essentially that is what HTML is all about.
It is about code.
Code that is made up of tags.
And these things are interpreted by our browser.
So what you're going to be learning is to write this code.
So that's it.
That's what we're going to be covering in this course HTML introduction to HTML.
We hope you're excited.
We're excited.
Yep.
See you on the other side.
All right.
See you there.
So get your brain ready your fingers warmed up.
And let's get learning about HTML.